uh welcome back to our new year's
program
and i wanted to thank all the
translators i can say some of you now
and suggeng emily
aldo thank you guys your other
translators
and you're doing a great job
and this is a special three-day program
uh free of charge for new year's
and
inspired by our singapore team and jenny
wong and her team so
thank you for
sponsoring this program thank you for
organizing it
thank you arena thank you amelie thank
you zonda
okay uh tim can i share my screen
you should have this you should have the
power to do that all right here we go
let's see
[Music]
okay
so
we're going to review a little bit about
what we did yesterday
what we went over
these are 12
different posters
based on the very rare paintings
uh
from the
harold temple howell new jersey in
america there's a small mongolian temple
called rashi gampalin
and i studied there for 25 years with my
teacher
and i'm very grateful
to this temple
uh without that temple
i wouldn't be able to
[Music]
i'm still hearing somebody
so i just wanted to thank the temple
and this is where we found
these 15 very rare paintings uh that
reached the temple even before i got
there
uh yesterday we talked about the lessons
from
these 15 paintings i think the most
important lesson is
we need a teacher
and uh
i'll tell you something interesting if
you ever see
emptiness directly
if it ever happens to you
that you can see emptiness directly
of course many amazing things happen to
you
it's possible you'll have a direct
experience of bodhichitta
and at that moment you meet every single
person
in the universe directly
and you talk to them
and you say
i will take care of you in in this life
i will take care of you and future lives
but i think uh a more amazing
thing that happens at that moment if you
if you want to know
is you see your future teachers and you
see who will teach you in your future
lives
and that's a very wonderful
experience because you can see the
teachers
who will teach you even when you're a
little kid
in your next life and your future lives
so it's a it's a wonderful experience
when you see emptiness directly
that you know
you will be taken care of
into your future lives
by teachers and you will have the karma
to meet those teachers
so it's a wonderful reason to see
emptiness directly
i i don't think you can reach the goals
of
these paintings without finding uh your
heart teacher
and we said yesterday
it's like a pair of jeans you know the
same genes don't fit everybody
in fact i don't think
there's two people in the world who wear
the same genes exactly
and you know you have to find the
teacher who fits you
and then always remember
that this teacher is coming from you
they are coming from your seats
and the way you find the teacher
is the same way you find a husband or
wife you plant the seeds
uh that they will come to you
and
they will come to you like a bee coming
to honey if you plant the seeds you
don't have to
you know i i found
i found this temple
and i found this teacher this great
great geshe
uh about 45 minutes from princeton
university first i went to uh india to
look for them in himalayas
and then later i just plant the seeds
and and they come to me
that's the first painting we covered
yesterday
uh
secondly we said that there is a reason
uh you came to this life
uh
you know when you're a little kid
you always start to think that maybe
there's some reason
why i came to this this life you know
maybe i'm supposed to do something
special
in this world i think all
all all of us
when we are
kids we start to think
oh there must be some special reason why
why i came to this world there are there
are billions of worlds the new telescope
went up uh
two three days ago
that telescope can detect uh
the very
the very last vibrations from the
beginning of the universe
and we've been there uh there are
countless worlds it proves there are
countless worlds billions and billions
and there must be people on on other
worlds
and yes our purpose
why we came into one world why we came
to this world
is we're supposed to do something here
each one of us is supposed to do
something here
and i'm very proud that almost everybody
listening today i i think almost
everybody listening today
they are helping
in some way
to spread these teachings and to help
other people in the world
to understand these beautiful teachings
and uh sorry cutter i just want to thank
all of you
i i believe
almost every person in the singapore
group or the other groups that are
listening here
i know you are working hard i'm looking
at tim right now
he's uh
he's working from early morning to late
at night uh all the time
and there are many many people like that
in this group and i'm very grateful to
you
you did come here to save the world
it is what you're supposed to do
you were right when you were a little
kid
you're supposed to do something special
and never doubt it okay never done it
you're not here to eat and
and poo poo and and die this is not why
you are here
you are here to do something special
for the world and you have the tools
you have these paintings these teachings
you you came here for a reason
and you're supposed to help this whole
world and you can
and many of you are doing it and i think
you
i think you don't even think about it
much
uh you're just doing it but
sometimes you should
sit down and say wow i'm doing good
stuff you know i'm really doing good
stuff
i'm really out of the world
i didn't come to
to eat and poo poo and die you know i i
came here
to this world to do something special
and i am a special person and you are
okay
all right now we come to by the way here
you can see uh
this is uh
a little booklet i wrote
uh many years ago
about the paintings what's happening in
the paintings
and
uh
if you like
uh you can get a copy of this
little booklet it's basically what i'm
teaching
and you can get a copy of this booklet
we're kind of bribing people if you do
if you help with one of our projects
charity projects we will we will send
you this booklet
okay new painting for today uh a new
topic
is question everything you know
uh always ask questions and go deeper
you know i love it uh when i go to
singapore
uh when i go to asia
i will ask the audience you know
hey you guys want to go deeper
and they always go crazy like yay we
want to go deeper you know
and oftentimes in the class people will
complain to me gesla
today you didn't go deeper about
emptiness or you know you didn't make us
you didn't debate with us you didn't
question us
uh let's go deeper let's go deeper okay
so
that's very much a tradition
of songkapa uh in our tradition
we ask a lot of questions
we go deeper
and especially we go deeper into the
ancient books
uh we
we talk
to the ancient masters there are 2
500 years
of ancient masters
and you can talk to them if you just
read their books you know
those books are very difficult and and
very very difficult to understand
but you cannot go deeper
you cannot make real spiritual progress
unless you ask questions and i love this
example here i'm gonna blow up this
picture
this is uh this golden guy
that's always some copper in this
paintings okay
so
in this painting he's 15 years old
okay
and he left his home
in east of tibet
and he walked
to lasa it's many hundreds of miles over
the snow mountains
over the rivers there's no bridges at
that time
he walked
when he was 15 years old
he he walked to the capitol
why
because that's where the great
monasteries are
that's where you can become a geshe
that's where you can study the great
books and he purposely walked he walked
all the way
the hundreds and hundreds of miles he's
15 years old
okay
and on the way
he didn't just visit a bunch of temples
and stop at monasteries
every time he goes to a monastery
he says you guys can i sleep here
tonight
i'm going to
study in the great
monasteries and people say yeah sure you
can sleep here tonight
can i have some food yeah you can have
some food
don't forget he's 15 years old then he
says can i debate with all the monks in
your monastery you know can we debate
and he's like a cowboy
who wants to show his uh
how fast he can shoot his gun you know
he's like uh can i debate with the monks
in your monastery
so he in the paintings we see him this
is a dewachen
a monastery called derochen on his
walking
to study at the great with the great
teachers
he debated
the whole way okay every painting here
you can see uh some copper in the golden
color
uh he's debating with these other monks
and he's asking them questions
and he's exploring news like new ideas
and we really really have to do the same
and this is our tradition
uh in our tradition sokapa tradition
we we say
actually we're not allowed to study the
easy things
uh we're supposed to concentrate on the
difficult things okay
and
tim
can we show the mixed nuts class
announcement there's a mixed nuts class
coming up in
february
this is 60 hours
of
of deep deep uh exploration
of the ancient books okay and it's very
difficult
and it's very confusing
and it's very exhausting for us in
arizona
we get up early in the morning
and we work until late at night
so that people from europe
and people from asia can come
so here you can see the class this is
mixed nuts
these are the
uh great translators from all over the
world
who are
studying how to translate the ancient
books
and we are taking the top books
we are not translating the easily books
we are translating the the most
difficult books
because we are afraid in the future
those books won't be available
in modern languages so you're welcome to
take a shot of this barcode
and
a qr code
and you can uh come to the classes
and go deeper this is our tradition this
is the songkapa
tradition
uh tim
we have two new books came out from this
group
very very uh deep books
first one
is called emptiness meditations
maybe you can show that slide tim
[Music]
and this is a new book
just came out
and it's in english for the first time
it has the most ancient
directions
how to meditate by kamala sheila
a very very famous uh
bhavanakrama his famous book on how to
meditate
and then it has uh 38
different uh emptiness meditations
that you can try 23 of those meditations
are
are correct
and 15 of them are wrong
okay
and i think it's very beautiful that
this book
which was written
above
350 years ago
the author tony lama
he says look here's 23 good emptiness
meditations
and here's 15 wrong emptiness
meditations okay
and
you have to be careful not to do them
okay so it's a wonderful book it's very
very valuable
i hope you will use the qr code get a
copy
and we're translating it into other
languages also
this was translated by
venerable udbala bets grier
uh who's one of our mixed nuts
translator
and she did a great job and she's
working very very hard
to prepare all of the books for you guys
she's she's working incredibly hard
uh every day
i saw her the other day for dinner and
her eyes are uh the water is coming out
of her eyes all the time because she's
working so long hours
her eyes are
are always watering
from the editing
all the translators book
tim i'd like to show another book
it's called the golden key
and this book uh came out
yesterday
okay the ebook
uh
tim if you need it there's a email in
your email from rosa
about with with this graphic okay
uh
and this is a book
uh translated by word smith
he's a
mixed nuts translator
and the golden key is a famous famous
book
about the middleweight school sorry mind
only school
and this is a
very very difficult
subject
in the monastery in the geshe course
we don't study the mind only
especially we don't have a separate
course specifically for mind only school
we study it while we are studying
some middleweight teachings
but this is a great great book
i think it's the greatest
beginning book
about the mind only school
that you can ever use
and it goes very deep
about how the world is coming from your
mind
and i really this is the first day we've
announced this book
it was finished late last night
uh
the e-book was finished late last night
i'd like to thank rosa van griecken
and also
venable jigme ellie van der poss
and the whole team
at the diamond cutter press is working
very hard
and word smith
boy he worked so hard
he worked for five years
to translate this book i think it's the
greatest book available
for the mind only school
and i encourage you to get it i like
this ebook format
well we already sold the
we only sold the physical books
like this is the
diamond cutter suitor commentary
uh that we printed about i don't know
three years ago
and ellie and i worked on it for 20
years
and
i didn't like ebooks you know i like to
read the real book
but uh during the coven
we can't get a paper we can't get
publishers
it's difficult to get shipping
and we started to do ebooks
and the first time i saw the ebook i was
so happy i said oh man
i've been so stupid
uh in the past not to use these ebooks
you know you can send them
i like to buy them and send them to my
friend it takes about three minutes you
know you go to diamond cutter press
website
here's the qr code
and you can send it to all your friends
and it's so much fun
for me to send a book to my friends it
takes about
less than three minutes
and i'm very happy to see this book come
out and i'd like to thank oh there's
word smith hi word
uh
this is his really
he's done a lot of great work as a
translator
he has
finished a huge dictionary
chinese language tibetan language
english language
and
he's worked very very hard and this is
his great achievement he's working on
a follow-up book which goes even deeper
and word i think we can finish in about
six more years don't worry
okay
and then i hope we can do some more but
the mind only school is really uh
the basis of all buddhism in china all
chinese people doesn't matter where you
live
uh the mind only school
is the basis of of your ancient
traditions and uh i think it's one
reason why
chinese people are so successful in the
world
chinese speakers is because it doesn't
matter what country you live in
but i think it's because of the
influence of the mind only school
and learning it and it's very very
important to learn and very valuable so
i hope you guys get that book hey tim
can i go back to my
thank you word good job um i'm going to
go back to where is that
here we go
so there's soga he's going deeper
he's debating
he's look there he is debating again uh
don't forget he's like 15 years old okay
and here he's debating again
uh why why we debate like uh martial
arts uh wushu why we use this uh
like karate uh or wushu
format for debating i'll tell you my
theory
uh the monks don't get any exercise
in the monastery
and
we do two three hours a day of debating
and you're exhausted
uh when you come home and also the monks
get very strong
from debating and also they're not
allowed to have a girlfriend at that
time
so i think it gets all this energy
out by debating and it's a very
beautiful custom and they go very very
deep
and they they learn a lot okay
uh
here's another
this is an interesting part of this
painting
and i'll tell you something going on
here
uh
so kappa is debating manjushri
okay this is unbelievable you know later
in his life
he learned how to meet uh this buddha
called manjushri directly the one with
the sword here
uh let me get my big
cursor
[Music]
hang on
oh i can't do that okay
all right anyway here's my juicery up in
the top
and so kappa is actually debating with
him and asking him questions about
emptiness so
he's even debating with the buddha all
right
here's he uh also studying lamrim asking
questions
to his teacher and he
i have some students uh i can think of
some of you
who are always asking me questions
and
i like it okay i like it i like to
answer questions
and it's it's very much our tradition
that we ask questions we go deeper
i had some people uh from
some people i know they told me you guys
talk too much
you know you should meditate more you
know you shouldn't uh
always talk about philosophy you know
you should
you should have a good heart
uh you should practice compassion but
actually you can't practice compassion
if you don't understand emptiness okay
then your compassion is not real
compassion okay you need to ask
questions
you need to go deeper
and you need to to read words books and
books like that okay here's more uh
pictures of tonkapa
debating
uh throughout his life
and he never
he never finished he was debating uh
even to the end of his life
and it's a very good custom okay
so i encourage you guys
keep asking questions
keep
coming to those mixed nuts classes i i
had somebody told me
uh gesla i went to words class online
i went to the mind only class in the
mixed nuts
and i didn't understand one thing
you know for one hour i didn't
understand one thing
and i said that's good okay that means
you're learning something okay if you go
to a class
by some teacher
and you understand everything easily you
say i heard that before i understand it
then think about it
you're not learning anything new
you are not improving yourself okay so
you have to
go deeper
you have to study the ancient books
these ancient writers were genius they
were super einstein
they also know
500 years ago 2 000 years ago
their meditation is very good they know
you are going to read their book in 2000
years they can see it directly
so actually the book is written for you
it's very interesting okay those books
are not
normal books you don't read them
and put them on the shelf and you don't
finish a buddhist book you never finish
a buddhist book you live with the book
for your whole life
okay and
you're not supposed to finish
just keep going deeper and deeper and
deeper okay
uh
and and your mind will expand then you
can really have love for other people
then you can really help other people
okay
so it you need to study
it's a big part of our tradition
you need to go deeper
if you want to help people okay and you
need to ask questions and in this
tradition
we encourage you to ask questions if
you're bothering the teacher
you're asking more questions you are not
bothering the teacher the teacher likes
it we like it okay
all right uh
if you keep asking questions
then
one day
we say you will see the diamond and this
is our
fourth goal
of these paintings and these are all
pictures
from the paintings of the temple in new
jersey
these are all pictures
about sankarpa seeing emptiness directly
okay in this picture
here
he starts to have a strange uh
he starts to have a strange he's
meditating
he's in the class
and then suddenly he looks up in the sky
and he sees
the mother sutras he sees
the emptiness teachings written on the
sky
okay like he's so
deep into emptiness teachings
and he's so deep into understanding the
books of emptiness probably it's words
book i guess
uh
but he looks up at the sky
and he sees the book i guess it's even
faster than the ebook
he looks at this guy
and he sees the emptiness teachings
written on the sky
you know and
it means he's going to see emptiness
soon he's going to see emptiness
directly soon
this is a beautiful scene here uh where
he
has a vision
of
all the great teachers of emptiness
especially in the gardener so i'm gonna
blow this up
this and remember these paintings are
tiny
this nagarjuna is uh smaller than your
thumb okay than your thumbnail
and these painters uh my teacher told me
the ones who painted these paintings
many of them went blind later you know
they they they are painting the garagina
with a single horse hair
they are painting this painting it's
okay and
here
if you look carefully you can see uh
snakes
around the guardian's head
and that means he's the king of the
nagas
why
why that is because
he went to the
world of the nagas to get the emptiness
teachings so here at some kaapa is
is seeing a vision
of the great teachers of emptiness and
if you want to
really go deep into emptiness come to
the mixed nuts classes
and nick professor nick lashaw his
his book
is all from the gardener
he's finishing i think
he just finished
a great sorry he's going to finish in
february
a great great book about lagoona
and then he's going to start another one
which will take about six more years so
if you're really interested
in these deep deep teaching song on
garjana
then
come and listen to nick's class and also
i will be teaching negotiate wisdom
for aci we will have another course
coming up soon uh tim i forgot what
month uh july we'll be releasing it
oh okay
all right and we're going through the
regards in this book so when
sao kappa
was about ready to see emptiness
directly
he had this vision of nagarjuna
and the great teachers of emptiness okay
i love this painting
so we
i gave some of the paintings from the
mongolian temple in new jersey
i gave them to a young artist in new
york city
his name is oriken
some of you know him he's a good teacher
and i said can you paint it uh
modern style
western style you know can you paint it
a little bit modern style and he did and
this is a very famous
uh
place just before uh some copper
emptiness
he had a vision
of manjushri
and that's up on the top here
and from manjushri's heart
came a sword
came out of the heart a sword made of
light
and it struck sonkaba in the heart
and that's supposed to be
the trigger
of when songkappa saw emptiness directly
so it's very very cool
[Music]
uh
and here manjushri is in the bottom left
he's predicting that tsunkapa will see
emptiness right after he saw nagojna
he saw emptiness directly
yeah you can do it okay you can all do
it you have to study the great books
and you have to meditate every day okay
here's the explanation
you can get this
copy now poster number five i think it
is
uh
and i'm trying to finish them all today
tim i'm maybe i will be a little slow
it says you should meditate okay you
should learn to meditate and this first
picture is socappa
he left his home
when he was 15 and he never went back
he never saw his mother again he loved
his mother very much
but he left he went to the mountains
he started to meditate
and he he learned how to meditate
properly
correctly
i like this uh white teacher here in the
white
he's a ningma
yoga master
from niigma means the old tradition into
that
and son kappa is asking for his help
to learn how to meditate
and
you know these great teachers they're
always showing us
something about ourself
you know and so kama
he he listened how to meditate
how to use prana or chi in his
meditation
from this nigma master
and the ningman master said do you have
any questions you want to ask me
and if you can read tibetan you can see
here it says
means uh
what song asked the great meditation
master he said
i don't have problem with meditation
i have problem with my back
could do means in my back you know my
back hurts
when i meditate my legs hurt when i
meditate can can you help me
uh how do i fix that you know and he
taught him yoga
the meaning of asana
the meaning of yoga
pose
is really a meditation pose and he
learned yoga
from this master
and he learned how to sit
without his legs hurting without his
back hurting and he had
some carpet had this problem his whole
life
his legs hurt when he meditated his back
hurt
and i think he's trying to show us look
uh even the great teachers have these
problems
and you have to be tough
and you have to overcome those problems
okay
i like this picture okay this is very
cute i love this story
if you think about it
if your meditation is perfect
it means you
you
put your heart on
your your senses withdraw you don't see
anything
you don't hear anything
if somebody put a mcdonald french fry
close to your nose
you won't smell it even you you withdraw
from your sense organs
and then there should be a problem right
if your meditation is perfect
then
then how to wake you up okay
and uh i used to think about this
problem you know i used to think what
would happen if my meditation is perfect
then i will never get up you know i
would just keep going maybe i will die
on the chair and this is a real story in
this picture
uh tonkapa went uh to a a prayer meeting
with all the monks
uh which we're gonna do tomorrow in
arizona and i encourage you guys to do
tomorrow
uh in the morning we're gonna meet
together we're going to meditate
then we're going to do the last class
and eat together and celebrate the new
year
and tomorrow
we are all going to make our resolutions
okay so tomorrow we'll go through the
paintings again
and we'll make some promises for the new
year every one of us i also need to make
some promises okay
so anyway this story is so beautiful so
kappa
went into meditation
during a group
meditation in the temple
and he forgot to get out of meditation
everybody else
that they announced the meditation is
finished they all got up they all left
the temple
and then they realized he's still in the
temple 10-12 hours later
somebody said where's son cuppa
i said i don't know where did he go and
then they went back to the temple
and he's still in meditation because he
didn't hear the bell
to tell him to finish the meditation
okay and i think that's a great
concentration
i think that's a really wonderful here
he's learning how to meditate
and he's getting uh different
instructions
on how to maintain here he's at the
raden monastery
which is atisha's old monastery
and he's teaching his students how to
meditate okay
and you see he's probably using kamala
sheila's book
which you can read in the emptiness
meditations book okay
all right uh
and here
uh he's getting again help
he's and i like he's in his meditation
chamber
and he's getting advice
on how to go deeper into his meditation
from manjushri okay himself
uh i like this painting this is uh
supposed to be the last year
of sao koppa's life and he was uh he was
62 i think
yeah he was 62 years old
in tibet they didn't live very long
in the old days
and this is the last year of his life
and he's if you can see he's sitting in
a tent
why he's sitting in a tent
uh he's outside they went camping
in the in the forest okay why did they
go camping in the forest
there's a hot spring
in the forest hot water
coming out of the ground
and some carpa's legs were bothering him
in meditation he had arthritis
in his legs and he asked his students
uh i i want to meditate but my legs hurt
please carry me
to the hot water spring
and let's put my legs in the hot water
and then i can meditate longer
so even to the last year of his life
he's trying to meditate longer and
longer okay and i i think it's a
beautiful thing
all right that's the
that's another resolution we can make
for the new year
okay now we're on number
what is that
number six maybe
i think so
uh i'm going to
talk about this painting for a while and
then i'm going to introduce a special
guest that we have
uh
there's a tradition in buddhism that we
should ask
angels for help okay
here's a beautiful picture
here
on the left side
and
so this is syncopa's mother
and she's asking
the angels for help you know
she wants to know
can she have a baby
can't she have a special baby
and she even started to talk to the
angels about her baby okay
so
sometimes when you meditate
uh it's very good to just close your
eyes
and say
please send me a message you know
angels please send me a message okay you
can call buddha's or angel doesn't
matter
you can close your eyes in the
meditation
especially if you're having some trouble
or something
and you can ask
the angels please send me a message
please send me a message today
okay i will watch today
for your message you know and then
you will get some uh funny messages
yesterday
hey tim i went to camp verdi i'm
desperate to go to a coffee shop
there's no coffee shop around here open
after two o'clock it's terrible
and i heard this when it's open till 2
30.
so i went there and
this old man came in
he's way overweight
and uh
he looks to be 70
now 70 doesn't look
old to me let's say 75
and uh he can't walk very good
and he's with his wife and
and they buy some bad food they buy some
uh you know like donuts
wait wait
we got yo chow
and
he starts to eat the donuts and i'm
thinking
man
that's gonna kill you you know to eat
this bad food
you already already he almost cannot
walk you know
and he's talking to his wife
they're both very old you know and i was
listening okay maybe i'm not supposed to
listen but um
that's why you go to a coffee shop right
tim
you like to listen to the people you
know and he told his wife
no
and she said yes and he said no
and she said yes and he said no you
cannot make your meditation short today
you cannot you have to do the whole
meditation you know
you cannot
make your meditation short you have to
do this whole thing
and then i'm like whoa
there's a cowboy in arizona
he's an old man he almost cannot walk
he's eating all these donuts
and the angels are sending me message
okay like did you do your meditation
today
they're sending me a message okay this
guy is a buddha
this guy is not a human being you know
and
you can get messages like that okay
uh
here's some messages that uh tonkata got
in this picture on the right he's
meditating
he's getting messages from atisha
and from a tantric deity
he's seven years old
okay he's seven years old in this
pleasure and he's already meeting angels
okay
uh when they did fundraising
for their big uh tempo for their big
monastery
uh he
invited this angel called vaishravana
and this is kubera this is the
the buddha of
fundraising okay
i think jenny wong and her group uh must
be talking to this angel because their
fundraising is so powerful
and
so he when he needed to raise funds
uh he would talk to this angel there's
one more angel i like here
this
angel this is a picture the hands are
the dalai lama's hands
he came to the mongolian temple many
many years ago when he was very young
we met him and he
he touched this young girl's face and it
was so beautiful
i was watching
and
she looked like an angel to me you know
and i'll never forget this
picture
that i saw at that moment
and uh this little girl named emily
uh we have another emily in our in our
group but this little girl became a
young woman
and
tim is islamily there and she was gonna
talk a little bit about
the mongolian temple they are still
fundraising
and uh
i thought maybe we could talk to this
age hi emily hi hi can you hear me
yeah and if you'd like to talk for five
ten minutes we'd love to hear about the
temple and
and what's up with the temple
um hello everyone my name is amelie
mitchell i have been a lifelong member
of the russia gambling temple
our family's been part of the
congregation
of the church about 70 years ago
the temple was built by our community
which included all my relatives
who trained many great scholars and
masters such as
rinpoche and triangulum
his legacy lives on throughout the world
having many students himself including
michael roach
when i was a child
my first teacher of buddhism
he would patiently teach us how to read
and write and tibetan and teach us
stories which explain the history of
buddhism and also how to determine right
from wrong
we grew up attending services each month
and of course for special holidays
including
which we celebrated last night and
for a lunar new year which we're looking
forward to celebrating in march
i will always cherish waking up before
the dawn to welcome the new year in the
temple it is so special and such a nice
way to start the year with our family
and other members of our congregation
our community revolves around the church
i got married in the church
yeah a few things um there's a strange
echo on your side is there a two
computers in your room
is that better
yes and could you slow down it by about
25 we have uh translators who are
translating into eight languages um
they're having a hard time following you
because we want our participants to be
able to hear everything you say
okay okay wonder wonderful is this
better
there's still an echo
yes there's still an echo
yeah is there a second computer in the
room
there is but it's not
it's at least you know you know it's not
on
um
maybe if you can turn down your volume
on your computer itself like the at the
output micro the output speaker
is that better
i think so
okay emily keep going take deep breaths
and then the translators have time to
translate
do you want me to start over or do you
want me to just keep going
i think it'd be nice to start over go
slow
okay okay okay
i'm sorry again everyone hello my name
is amelie mitchell and i've been a
lifelong member of the russia gambling
temple
our family has been part of the
congregation since the inception of the
church about 70 years ago
our temple was built by the community
which is is
his legacy lives throughout the world
having many students himself including
guess she michael
was my first teacher of buddhism
he would patiently teach us how to write
and read in tibetan
foreign
completely
new year
[Music]
thank you emily uh i apologize to
everybody that we had some technical
problems
but uh amelie is encouraging us uh
to
she's telling us how important is the
temple which was built
70 years ago
and how much it meant to her through her
whole life
she got married there
she also went to cluster as a young girl
and
again this book king of the dharma book
we have an e-book maybe tim you can show
the
and we have an e-book and we have a
physical book uh
and i would try to get a copy okay
and all of the prophet is going to go to
help uh russia gambling temple the
mongolian temple
and this book has three parts
uh the first part is about
amelie's
ancestors her family
you can see them in this pictures
the third part of the book is all of the
paintings
and the meaning of each of the paintings
you can see
each part of the paintings is there and
explained
and the middle part of the book
is how you can practice like two couple
and i encourage you to get a copy
uh through this
qr code
and uh
this new generation amelie
and zanda and all of their friends and
family
they are keeping this temple going
and i thank you emily for doing that
and thank you for being such a good
student she learned the
wheel of life
about how many years ago i think uh 40
years ago
at least 40 years yeah yeah yeah
she learned sugan she translated before
you did okay we worked on it before you
did
and uh they did a great job and thank
you for keeping this temple alive
and thank you for allowing me 25
beautiful years there thank you thank
you family for me okay
i will
all right
okay here we go back to
back to the painting
and there's amelia as a young girl
being greeting the dalai lama at the
temple i will never forget that
okay
uh
seventh picture
is uh it's tradition uh
that some member of your family
uh okay omni your husband
or
your wife or even your children
uh you will find
uh angel in your own family okay this is
an ancient tradition
that uh if you
listen carefully
to your family members
uh
you can hear angels talking sometimes uh
your kids
will say something to you
sometimes your husband
sometimes your wife
and so it's good to
to meet
uh
to to see
that even your family members like your
wife your husband girlfriend
boyfriend
can be also talk to you like a buddha
sometimes
so here's a beautiful uh
lady called tongsha mammal
and this was the the spiritual partner
of songkapa
later in his life
he had a partner named the she's called
the lady in the red hat
and this special hat uh tibetan style
hat is called tongsha
and everybody knows her as a tongsha
marmal the lady with the red hat and she
was his spiritual partner
later in his life and helped him to
reach emptiness
these two
spiritual partners on the sides
this is a female buddha
and a male buddha
and they were partners and they came to
tonkapa's mother
in a dream here you can see her sleeping
and she had a
dream that she's standing in a long line
of women
and these two partners spiritual
partners
they are walking down the line
and uh
the guy will ask the lady uh is this the
mother of tonkata and and she said no no
not this one
and they keep going down like a hundred
ladies
in the dream
and finally uh
the lady angel said yes this one this is
going to be some couple's mother
so this is a famous dream
of spiritual partners that some
copperhead
uh
this painting on the lower left is very
very famous
and uh
this uh
one monk is songkappa
and one monk is called toptemba
and so kappa was nervous to have a
partner he said well i'm a monk you know
it's a little bit difficult people won't
understand it
and
manjushri came
and these angels came you can see the
angels in the cloud
okay
and they started pouring uh
there was a dream
and they started pouring uh amerta
deathless nectar
on these different stupas here i i think
they're supposed to be seven but i think
there's i guess there's more here
uh
and so kappa said what does this dream
mean you know what what does it mean
that the angels are pouring
uh this honey
on the stupas
and
he got a message from manjushri
manjushri said
this means that you
and some of your students are ready to
have spiritual partner you can have a
spiritual partner now and i want you to
to find your partner
and i want you to practice together with
her
so here's a traditional kind of painting
where you can see these partners
and i think this is a cute uh
this is a cute meditation that zomcapa
did
when i think he was about 20 years old
and
he never wrote anything before
he never wrote
any writing before
and he had a vision
of tara oh sorry sorry swati
which is here this is the goddess of
music
this is the buddha of music the female
buddha
of music and
i like it in our buddhism that we have
female buddhists and and man buddhists
we have both
so this is a female buddha
she specializes in
religious music
and uh
he had a vision of her and he had a
relationship with her
uh at the age of 20 and he wrote some
poetry to her
he wrote some beautiful poetry you can
see it here
and maybe someday in the mixed nuts we
can read this poetry
it's very very beautiful uh what he
wrote to his
to his muse okay
all right steph i gotta speed up i know
tim i'm trying okay
we have to finish twelve times
oh my gosh and tomorrow don't forget
we're gonna review and we're gonna go
deeper okay
and we're gonna make some resolutions
for for next
year
uh this is called be grateful
and say thank you to people
uh this is a beautiful uh thing that
happened
uh
so some kappa was studying
from a teacher called rendawa and
randallah is a sakya
sakya scholar
and he met randallah and randawa started
to teach him
and rendava wrote some famous book about
nagarjuna
and i hope we can translate that
but this is called about a bowing fight
they are having a bowing fight and you
can see it in the monastery
when one great teacher
meets the other great teacher
each one want to bow
like i used to go to the airport in
kyoto or tohoku
in japan
and you can see japanese people they're
having bowing fight each one trying to
bow more times or bow lower lower lower
lower
and it means thank you it means thank
you and it's showing gratitude okay
so what you see here is a bowing fight
each one want to bow to the other one
each one want to bow deeper to the other
one
uh some kappa
even
used to
show gratitude
to the books
okay so usually you can see him here in
the yellow hat
and he's holding a stick of incense this
is a package of incense
and when a great person
comes into the room
you're supposed to show gratitude to
them
and
and and burn this big incense package
and for example if the dilemma comes to
the mongolian temple they will
burn this
whole package of incense
and
sankapo wants to show his gratitude
to the 10 ream chamo chen rim chimo
is the mother of the lamb this is the
mother book
1 000 years ago
of the alam rim it's the first lamrim
that was ever written a thousand years
ago and
the book was lost
in some corpus time the book was lost
and one of his students found a copy
and in this picture uh so copper is
saying thank you to the book okay and
they are carrying the book on their back
the monks are bringing the book on their
back
and it's a big big book you know so i
think they split it up and he's showing
gratitude
for this
huge book it's two thousand pages
it's the mother of all lump rooms and
he's showing great gratitude to the book
i'll tell you a beautiful story
uh this book was lost
again
about a hundred years ago
and uh there were no copies in the world
and uh
john brady
and his team
found the copy
uh
in russia
and they
input the whole book
it's now it's free online uh on their
database their database has 16 million
pages
of great books and this book is one of
them
and it's all free the database is free
a lot of you guys help support this
singapore team especially and thank you
for that
uh okay i gotta go i know tim
okay one more thing okay two more thank
yous here we can go over tim a little
bit
yeah yeah
he's getting mad okay
this uh look at this guy here
you see uh he's a boy
with a rosary crystal rosary okay
and this is the past life of songkapa
before he came to this world
and he met a buddha this buddha
in his previous life he met a buddha
and he was just a boy okay
and the buddha taught him about
emptiness
and then uh
sam kappa was so grateful
that he offered the buddha this rosary
made of crystal
so he couldn't do a diamond roser it's
too expensive right so he said
these crystals
represent diamond
and by offering
this rosary to the buddha i pray
in my future life
i can teach emptiness to many people i
pray
in my future life
i can teach emptiness which is like a
diamond
to many many people and then he offered
this uh rosary out of gratitude
and then he did become an emptiness
teacher uh in in this world okay
uh i love this story there's one more i
want to show you let me see
oh this is uh tomkharpa he's i think
he's uh
seven years old
and he's taking his first vows
from the karmapa of his time
so this is a karmapa about 600 years ago
and tonkarpa is getting his first baby
vows
he's like his bodhisattvas
and his mother is teaching him how to
show gratitude they are offering some
scarves to the teacher
and this is his grandma i guess and they
are offering
they are showing gratitude to the karma
so really som kappa had soccer teachers
nima teachers
kaguya teachers
he's a master of all these traditions
okay i'm going faster faster faster
faster
look for the good in other people okay
look for the good in other people
try to
don't
don't waste your time okay guess what's
69 years old okay emily
now he's old man
you know me when i'm a young man
and um
i didn't learn a lot of things but i
learned one thing don't waste your time
thinking about stupid people okay don't
think about them don't talk to them
don't worry about them
don't talk to other people about them
if you see
in tibet they say
if you meet a bad person
then just turn away and walk away okay
there's a funny uh
there's there's a funny saying tim do
you remember uh
don't smell a fire twice
if someone makes a fart
okay and the smell is bad in the room
then just leave the room okay don't
don't
smell again and again try to find out
who's making the smell okay
uh
don't waste your time
thinking about people are bad or people
are mean or people said something to you
just walk out you know and go look for
good things in people you know there's
so many good people in the world
uh you don't have to worry about
uh the bad people okay save your time
that's how geshe-la did so many
translations and
teaching in so many countries i don't
waste my time
looking for bad in people just look for
the good things in people this is a
beautiful painting
here's the original painting down here
and some copper is meeting one of his
teachers
and uh
he said suddenly the teacher looked to
him like uh
like yamantaka
like a tantric
buddha you know
and suddenly tonkava looked like
manjushri so these two
so kaba is meeting his teacher
and the teacher sees songkappa turned
into manjushri
and so kappa see the teacher turned into
yamataga and here's
here's uh ori karen's painting
you see uh this is soncapa he
he became manjushri
and his teacher became a tantric daily
also
and it means
they saw the good in each other they saw
the good things there is something good
in every person in the world and you can
meet them
and enjoy the good things in other
people don't waste your time
thinking about somebody stupid or
somebody said something bad about you
don't waste your time okay
all right next picture where is the
don't forget we're going to make some
resolutions about this tomorrow
this is do your yoga hey geshe-la likes
to
kesla loves to
make bets with his students okay emily
i'm sorry in your time i didn't do this
but nowadays i will give the student
hundred dollars if they give me a good
answer
okay so you guys ready hundred dollars i
will give a hundred dollars
if someone can tell me
why this picture is important today
this is son kappa riding a tiger
as a yogi as a yoga teacher okay so
kappa
as a yoga teacher
riding on the tiger okay i'll give a
hundred dollars tim you watch watch the
chat
yeah that looks like a lot i would have
to this year the tiger
yeah that's correct answer who got it
alona
okay did
dollars then uh xiaoping has to try to
get the money to them okay
good luck
yeah it's the year of the tiger starting
a day after tomorrow okay starting
tomorrow
that will be the year of the tiger okay
and this is a famous famous uh painting
it's actually a
block print
that i got from mongolia emily i was
given this in mongolia
and
this is a famous vision
that kid jay had
uh after tsongkapa died
and he saw his teacher come to him in a
dream
and he's riding a tiger
and he's dressed like a yoga teacher
okay this is the ancient yoga teacher's
dress okay and it means
spiritual practice especially with a
partner
especially uh yoga is difficult
and it's like riding a tiger okay
you can go very fast
but you shouldn't fall off if you should
do your exercise every day
keep healthy
and keep doing your yoga every day okay
uh
this other picture the circle picture
is the 80 mahasidas of yoga
and this is a vision that so kappa had
these are all yoga teachers
from ancient india okay
here's a beautiful uh
carving that john brady
team
brought from
russia hey petersburg
and these are all the yoga poses which
here tonkata is studying
uh these yoga poses
how to do these yoga poses okay and
these are called the yoga poses of
naropa
uh from the six yogas of naropa
and socappa studied them
and throughout his life he did yoga it's
a great way to stay healthy
it's a great way to lose weight
you can have a lot of energy
even when you're older okay here's the
book you can see
and this book also came from mongolia
by the way this book here
is tim another hundred dollars
you
ready
someone has to tell me
why is this carving these circles
why why they carve these lines like this
in this yoga book why
a word said poses
nah
a word should pay me a hundred dollars
uh pigment said music
yeah i think it's right
she makes it right okay
so listen
to me
can't change
[Music]
so this is actually how to put music in
the ancient books
uh it tells you how to go up how to go
down okay
and that's a part another part of yoga
practice
all right which brings us to the next
painting
and
sometimes you should sing
sometimes you should dance
and sometimes you need to have fun
the most important uh festival in tibet
is
in the mongolian calendar
but
this is uh
the great prayer festival
and they dance
and they sing
and they have fun
and they eat too much
okay
just like christmas time uh here is some
copper here he's dressed up like an
angel
and he's doing angel dance okay he's
learning
how to do the sacred dance okay
and
here's a very rare photograph
from the 1940s uh an american military
plane
crashed in tibet
and the
captain of the of the plane was a
the nephew of tolstoy
from russia
he was an american captain and
he took some very rare photographs
when they got stuck into bed
and these are called angel dress this
means
the monk will dress up
like a lady
and they will sing and they will dance
and they will pretend that they are
angel
they are authentic diddy
so can we do it nowadays this is jimi
hendrix when he visited arizona long ago
you know can we do this kind of practice
uh
nowadays
uh i'm gonna try to
hey tim let me see if i can do this
[Music]
hang on you guys
okay let me try again
can you see it
[Music]
that's uh stanley doing spiritual music
okay i got one more to show you guys
so
here it is from the top
[Music]
[Applause]
but you can do something in between
[Music]
okay okay
it means uh sometimes if john brady can
can play music
and sing like and stanley can sing like
that
then uh sometimes celebrate sometimes
have fun okay that's part of some
copper's tradition
sometimes we should have fun tim i'm
going fast i'm going to finish soon one
more one more one more
okay
uh
the last one
uh the last painting is about doing
retreat okay and we should learn
uh how to do retreat
uh
here's the great retreat teacher uh
miller repa
in tibet
uh
teaching us how to do retreat uh
hey cap
how old was milo ripa when he started
his med
his uh retreats how old was he
do you know
he was old he was 50
he was 50.
okay he started to do his retreats
when he was 50. in tibet it's like 80 at
that time okay he started the most
famous retreat master in tibet
started to do his retreats when he's 50
something
so don't tell me you're too old to do
retreats cap did a three-year retreat
john did a three-year retreat many
people here
did long three-year retreats
you always start with one day
then you do a weekend
then you do a week
then you do two weeks
then you do six weeks
and slowly you reach a three year
retreat
last picture i want to show today okay
i love this
painting you know and uh
this is uh
some kappa is crossing a river
uh called kyomo
because he wants to escape his students
okay
he's very famous he has thousands of
students
and my judiciary says
you're you're getting too famous
and you have too many students now
and you're so busy
and you're not doing your retreats and
you're not doing your meditation you
know
i want you to go
and and do a retreat do a nice long
retreat okay
then he said no no no manjushri you
don't understand you know i'm a famous
man
and i'm very busy
and i have many organizations and and
you know i have to
stay i i don't have time to go retreat
and my manjushri said when my teacher
okay emily this is what my teacher
always said ken rinpoche he says i'm the
teacher i'm the teacher
i'm the teacher i told you to go on
retreat
you go on retreat okay and leave the
students for a while
and go take a nice long retreat okay and
this is the answer
that son kappa got uh from manjushri and
he said you take eight students only
and you guys
go across the river
in this little boat this boat is made
from a skin of a yak by the way
and uh
there's no room for more students in the
in the boat and nobody can follow you
and and go away
and go do some uh deep retreat okay so
uh this is the last lesson uh that we
can learn from
songkappa and again i encourage you guys
to do your deeper treats
and and do your
you need you need to do retreat we spent
a lot of money
to buy diamond mountain
retreat center is a thousand acres it's
the largest retreat center in the united
states
that
cat
and
hana
and hanley and
cinema they are working so hard
to keep this retreat center open and
this spring
we hope to
invite people back for the first time
after the pandemic and and we have to do
uh deep retreats together it's very very
important
uh to do your deep retreats so please uh
don't forget about your treats tim
should we skip the question answer or
what what do you want to do
it's kind of late yeah well we have
you know there's a couple of things you
had planned to do around fundraising if
you wanted to do it today
i was gonna do them tomorrow
uh just one thing i'll repeat that
try to order this book
all the all the proceeds go to the
mongolian temple amelie's family and the
other families near their temple
and don't forget there's an auction
for a mug
that was used by
geshe-la for 25 years at the temple
uh
and you're welcome to
to help support the temple in this way
uh tomorrow uh tim let's do the other
ones tomorrow that's okay i hope
okay
so i think we stopped there i'm sorry uh
geshe-la usually talks too much and
we'll try to do some questions and
answers tomorrow okay so what's the
schedule tomorrow
uh
in
in arizona
we will be uh meditating uh from seven
in the morning
that's one hour before the program
starts this program starts in asia
tomorrow 10 am i correct 11
p.m right
and then we will go for one hour
until midnight
and then we'll celebrate the new year
together so arizona time
8 a.m
for this program
uh tomorrow the class will be open to
mainland china students
i'm not allowed to teach religion in
mainland china even by internet
so
we will we haven't had
mainland students here in these two days
but tomorrow
we will have a
new year's resolution new year's ideas
for the year of the tiger
and we're inviting all of our friends
from mainland china also so it will not
be a religious program tomorrow
but we'll talk about
ways to improve yourself
and how to have a better life
using these famous paintings okay so
we'll see you tomorrow 11 p.m
uh asia time 8 a.m
arizona time and i don't know how it
works in europe you guys are probably
like 4 p.m or something
okay uh although you guys are
gonna be
seven a.m right
okay something like that yeah
okay
all right
uh so thank you for coming emily thank
you so much for speaking
and please give my regards to all your
family and all the other families there
and i'm very proud of you
and i'm very proud to see you guys okay
all right
see you guys later tomorrow
thank you
okay bye